Studies show that just a single
meal high in saturated fat
can impair artery function
for hours after consumption.
In this 3-part video series, we'll look at
what saturated fat does to our body,
and how diet and exercise
can protect our arteries,
thus helping prevent our
#1 killer: heart disease.
Check it out.
"Saturated Fat Causes Artery
and Lung Inflammation"
We are only as old as our arteries.
What can we do to preserve
artery function as we age?
A poor diet and sedentary behavior
can lead to adverse aging processes,
like impairment of the little power
plants in our cells, which can result
in free radical formation, oxidative
stress, and inflammation, which leads
to artery dysfunction that can end in
the cardiovascular disease that ends us.
In a series of videos I did
about a decade ago,
I discussed this landmark research
showing that a single high-fat meal
could cripple artery function
within hours of consumption,
compared to no change
in the low-fat meal.
The high-fat meal that so
crippled artery function included
Sausage and Egg McMuffins
from McDonald's.
How do we know the sausage,
egg, or cheese was to blame?
What about the crappy
carbs in the biscuits?
We know because the low-fat meal
that didn't impair artery function
was a sugary mess
of carby Frosted Flakes.
And just when your artery
function finally starts to recover
five or six hours later?
Lunch time,
when your arteries may get
whacked with another load
of meat, eggs, dairy, or oil.
Why does it matter so much what
happens after a meal within your body?
Because most of us spend about 16
hours a day in that after-a-meal state,
constantly hammering our arteries.
No wonder cardiovascular
disease is our #1 killer.
And it doesn't just inflame the arteries
in our heart, but our lungs as well.
A high-fat challenge increases
airway inflammation
and impairs bronchodilator
recovery in asthma.
Have asthmatics cough up sputum
from their lungs four hours
after the same kind of high-fat
meal and inflammatory cells
shoot up in the high-fat meal group.
In terms of lung function, give
them two hits of their inhalers,
containing a drug called albuterol or
Ventolin, and their airways open up
as they should after the low-fat meal.
But after the high-fat meal, the same
inhaler doses don't work as well,
crapping out after a few hours
because of all the extra inflammation
in their lungs.
What you eat can determine
how well you breathe.
Okay, but that was asthmatics.
But even in nonasthmatic subjects,
you get the same spike
in inflammatory cells
in sputum coughed out of your lungs
four hours after eating what was,
in this case, a Jimmy Dean's
Meat Lovers breakfast bowl.
And there aren't only more
inflammatory cells; there's also
a doubling of the amount of
pro-inflammatory oxidized bad
LDL cholesterol sucked up
by the type of white blood cells
that go on to form foam cells.
Those are the cells that build up
the inflamed pus in your artery
wall that leads to heart attacks.
And all this happens within just
hours of eating pizza in this case.
The fat in your blood goes up
and so do your endotoxin levels.
Endotoxins are components
of bacterial cell walls,
and foods like meat can be so
contaminated with bacteria—
alive and dead—that they
accumulate endotoxins,
and we're talking about both
red meat and white meat.
But recent research published in
2020 suggests the main culprit
may not be endotoxins
after all, but the fat itself.
The saturated fat floating in your
blood after an unhealthy meal
may be inducing the inflammation
more directly. Either way,
we are accountable for
what we eat meal-by-meal
for the modification of the risk factors
for chronic metabolic disease.